Leo Hurwitz collection, 1910-1992, bulk 1925-1991
George Eastman Museum
- Series 8, Teaching, 1943-1990
  - Subseries 1, American Theatre Wing, 1949-1957
    - no title (Box C201)
      - [Legal pad with seminar notes], 1957 (Folder 14b)
        Notes for "Seminar in the Creative Film, some labeled "Wing" (possibly the American Theatre Wing) and "SRT-TV" (School of Radio Technique), and dated Summer 1957; student writing exercises. Materials originally gathered together inside the pages of a yellow legal pad.
      - [Unlabeled folder with seminar notes], 1949-1950 (Folder 14d)
        List of lectures and lecture notes headed "SRT" (School of Radio Technique); seminar session notes labeled "Theatre Wing"; diagrams; and clippings from newspapers and Life magazines.
      - Wing -- Fall 1952 (Folder 14e)
        Empty folder. May have originally housed one of the legal pads.
    - no title (Box BOXOS-6)
      - [American Theatre Wing course in television notes and outlines], 1950-1952 (Folder 3a)
        Outline of "Course in Television: Production and Direction"; notes on the fall 1950 Wing session #1; studio and control room diagram; notes on "Fall 1952 -- Wing"; letter from the American Theatre Wing Professional Training Program about future production direction course plans.
      - Wing -- Dec. 4, 1950 term, 1952-1954 (Folder 3b)
        Photocopies of "The Director's Job" by Hurwitz (1945); blank achievement reports for students; course notes; photocopy of "Television Speech at Talent Panel"; blank TV production facilities report from NBC; NBC set diagram; classwork by student from American Theatre Wing; and magazine clippings.
      - [American Theatre Wing TV courses -- notes and classwork], 1955-1956 (Folder 3c)
        Notes on film, editing, and TV direction courses; classwork by American Theatre Wing students.
  - Subseries 2, Bard College, 1984-1986
    - no title (Box C176)
      - [Flex folder labeled: Bard College notes & papers, 2 seminars, Spring 1985] (Folder 9)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's term at Bard College, including notes, film screening schedules, student assignments, and class lists with grades. Also includes a copy of the May 1985 "Film Folio" schedule from the New Community Cinema, Huntington, NY.
      - To Bard, 1985 (Folder 9a)
        Correspondence, notes, film screening schedules, and student assignments.
      - [Envelope labeled: Moderation papers], 1985 (Folder 9b)
        Two papers from Bard College students William J. Zide and Marc Adams.
      - Mid-term Papers, also final (2), 1985 (Folder 9c)
        Bard College student papers, with grades and comments.
    - no title (Box C232)
      - [First drafts of material used in preparing Bard case and procedure booklet from Ct. of Redhook], 1986 (Folder 14)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's case against Bard College, including summary of the case and Small Claims Guide for Town and Village Court.
      - Bard College -- correspondence, 1984-1986 (Folder 15)
        Correspondence and related materials about Hurwitz joining the Bard fellows program and Hurwitz's small claims court case against Bard for film rental fees. Includes list of films to be screened, publicity, and overview of class.
  - Subseries 3, Columbia University, 1946-1986
    - no title (Box C041)
      - Columbia Univ. -- visiting scholars, 1983-1986 (Folder 67)
        Memo to visiting scholars at Columbia University, campus map, Columbia libraries hours, and the 1983-1984 Columbia University Fact Book; letters designating Hurwitz as a visiting scholar and, one year later, reluctantly granting him an extension of privileges Hurwitz's request.
    - no title (Box C050)
      - Film-TV school catalogues, 1946-1949; 1956 (Folder 15)
        Motion-picture and television course catalogues from Columbia University, Institut des Hautes Études Cinématographiques (in French with English translation insert), SRT Television Studios/The School of Radio Technique, The New School for Social Research, and the Television Workshop of New York.
  - Subseries 4, General, 1930-1989; 1943-1989
    - no title (Box C011)
      - Misc. -- Strand (FF), 1962-1965; undated (Folder 9b)
        Material concerning a monograph on the work of Paul Strand, including correspondence from Strand. Also includes correspondence from Gilbert Seldes and Sigmund Koch; a film school proposal submitted to the Ford Foundation; and general Ford Foundation materials.
      - Film school and “The Fine Art of Film”, 1965; undated (Folder 12)
        Copies of Hurwitz's essays “To the Lincoln Center: Thoughts on the Need for a School of Film" and “The Fine Art of Film," with notes.
    - no title (Box C016)
      - [Correspondence from Stanley E. Salfas], 1976 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence from Hurwitz assistant Stanley E. Salfas about the possibility of arranging film screenings/seminars.
      - Film school -- curr. -- New School, etc., 1962; 1966-1967 (Folder 29)
        Material dating from the proposal for a school of film at the New School of Social Research and New York University. Includes correspondence, newspaper clippings, and journals relating to the structure of the curriculum.
    - no title (Box C033)
      - Class seminar, 1963-1965; undated (Folder 7)
        Handwritten notes marked "Class"; short synopsis of a film project titled "Dream of a City."
      - Leo Hurwitz personal -- from NET, 1965-1966 (Folder 42)
        Correspondence. Subjects include proposals for film schools at NYU and Lincoln Center.
    - no title (Box C034)
      - News lectures, 1946; undated (Folder 1c)
      - SRT-TV, 1949 (Folder 1e)
        SRT [School of Radio Technique] Television staging plan diagram; syllabus for "Films for Television" course; scripts for Call It a Day,The Monkey's Paw, and Casablanca; handwritten lecture notes. Also includes attendance sheets for class titled "T.V. Prod. & Dir. I - B," taught at 432 West 44th Street, NYC (The Actor's Studio).
    - no title (Box C038)
      - [Correspondence], 1973-1975 (Folder 7)
        Includes correspondence regarding screenings and symposia at Rhode Island School of Design, John Jay College (where Native Land received a negative response), New York Film Council, Antioch College, Museum of Modern Art, University of Massachusetts Amherst.
    - no title (Box C040)
      - Film school -- notes and drafts, undated (Folder 7)
      - Film school idea -- final draft -- correspondence -- Lincoln Center, Buffalo, Rockefeller, 1965-1969 (Folder 8)
        Correspondence, proposal and article drafts, and clippings regarding the establishment of film school at Lincoln Center and elsewhere. Correspondents include the Rockefeller Foundation; State University of New York at Buffalo; California Institute of the Arts; the Lincoln Center Fund; and Lincoln Center for the Performing Arts.
      - Film school plans (work sheets), undated (Folder 9)
        Proposed film school budgets, including budgets for editing, sound, camera, and projection equipment, and first year expenses.
      - ["Thoughts on the Need for a School of Film"], undated (Folder 10)
        Three copies of Hurwitz's essay, with notes.
      - Film school -- New School, Buffalo, Cali. Institute of the Arts, etc., 1965-1968 (Folder 11)
        Correspondence, clippings, and other materials related to the film schools at the California Institute of the Arts, Columbia University, Yale, the New School for Social Research, the Babelsberg School, the State University of New York at Buffalo, and European institutions. Includes the Winter 1965 issue of The Educational Record with article about the study of motion pictures in colleges and universities
      - Film school -- University of NY at Buffalo, 1967; 1969 (Folder 12)
      - State University of New York Purchase -- (Houghton), 1967 (Folder 13)
        Correspondence with Norris Houghton, Dean of Theatre Arts at the State University of New York at Purchase, regarding Hurwitz's advice on developing a stage, film, and television at the school.
      - Correspondence -- miscellaneous, 1958-1969 (Folder 18)
        Includes correspondence with the State University of New York at Buffalo and New York University regarding Hurwitz's upcoming talks and seminars.
      - Film facilities -- also "general" -- misc. letters, 1956-1961 (Folder 21)
        Personal and professional materials, including notes on film seminars and NYU workshops, and an American Theatre Wing Professional Training Program Catalog, with an envelope containing a copy of Hurwitz's birth certificate and headshots.
    - no title (Box C043)
      - Several current things -- Screenings, 1963 (Folder 3a)
        Includes a letter from Boston University School of Public Relations and Communications regarding position vacancy.
    - no title (Box C045)
      - Ideas for articles and book, 1943 (Folder 10f)
      - Current ideas at work, 1944 (Folder 10k)
    - no title (Box C050)
      - Film-TV school catalogues, 1946-1949; 1956 (Folder 15)
    - no title (Box C089)
      - Helsinki seminars etc. 3/31-4/9/89, 1988-1989 (Folder 49)
    - no title (Box C105)
      - [Seminar notes], 1969 (Folder 3l)
    - no title (Box C106)
      - Europe trip -- Rome, Berlin, 1988 (Folder 21)
        Notes and correspondence from Berlin regarding an additional seminar.
    - no title (Box C172)
      - New Institute for Film, 1951 (Folder 18)
        Correspondence and memos regarding payment and policies of the New Institute for Film and Television. Also includes a school catalog and course outlines and related notes.
    - no title (Box C178)
      - AFI interview transcript to be reworked, 1973 (Folder 15)
        Transcript of a 1972 seminar held by Hurwitz with the Fellows of the Center for Advanced Film Studies at the American Film Institute (AFI), with related correspondence.
    - no title (Box C186)
      - [File pocket labeled: Notebook -- Sarah Lawrence -- small negs. -- misc.], ca. 1930 (Folder 2)
        Leather notebook containing notes related to Hurwitz's class at Sarah Lawrence, including a list of appointments; notes on sessions and schedule; and introductory questions.
    - no title (Box C192)
      - History of movies, 1934 (Folder 2d.3)
        Notes for a series of lectures on the history of the movies, including technological development, "the hypnotic effect of the movies," nature of propaganda, class origin of movies, film as a weapon of the capitalists, and Terry Ramsaye.
    - no title (Box C201)
      - [Unlabeled folder with seminar notes], 1949-1950 (Folder 14d)
      - Class, 1957; undated (Folder 14f)
        Class notes, outlines, and shooting scripts.
    - no title (Box C227)
      - Films sent to William James College, 1979-1981 (Folder 34)
        List of Hurwitz films taken to William James College (1979); invitation to appear at the William James College 10th Anniversary Synoptic Lecture (1981).
  - Subseries 5, Kirkland College, 1972-1977
    - no title (Box C016)
      - [Postcard from Mike Krawitz], 1977 (Folder 7)
        Postcard to Hurwitz from Mike Krawitz regarding Hampshire College.
    - no title (Box C036)
      - Inventories -- "S.F.N.P." material to Kirkland, 1975-1976 (Folder 10)
    - no title (Box C103)
      - [Pd. bills Kirkland 9/75-1/76], 1975 (Folder 1b)
      - [File letters to 1/76], 1975 (Folder 1c)
        Personal and professional correspondence addressed to Hurwitz at Kirkland College. Correspondents include Nina Bogin; Marcus Schatner, MD; Janet Brof; Samuel Traum, CPA; Lewis Jacobs; Thomas Brandon, regarding his search for The World Today, Scottsboro, and the "ILD film" (most likely Sweet Land of Liberty); Bonded Services, regarding a decomposition inspection of Hurwitz's nitrate material; Rosetta Hurwitz; and George Stoney.
      - [Envelope labeled: Rollins/L.H. tape & 3 docs. of New Deal & letter], 1975-1976 (Folder 2d)
        Includes a copy of the essay "Ideology and Film Rhetoric: Three Documentaries of the New Deal Era" by Prof. Peter C. Rollins, with cover letter. Also includes a copy of "Public Fantasies," a Hamilton College poetry journal, and a 12/15/1975 Statement to the Faculty of Kirkland College. Envelope originally included an audiocassette tape recording of an interview with Hurwitz conducted over the phone by Rollins. This tape has been relocated to the box Hurwitz audio materials in the Stills, Posters, and Paper Collection.
      - [Envelope labeled: Blue's list of doc. films], 1975 (Folder 2e)
        Syllabus for James Blue's course "History and Problems in the Documentary Film" at the State University of New York at Buffalo.
      - Kirkland College, 1974-1975 (Folder 2f)
        Correspondence and grant-application documents related to Hurwitz's residency at Kirkland College. Also includes Stanley Salfas's résumé.
      - Résumés etc. LTH, 1972-1975 (Folder 2g)
        Includes a 10/10/1975 clipping from the Hamilton/Kirkland College newspaper The Spectator regarding Hurwitz; a poster for a screening of Native Land;Cineaste magazine vol. IV, no. 3 featuring an interview with Hurwitz; text of talk "Films of the 30's: A Socio-political Aesthetic" given by Hurwitz at a 2/19/1972 symposium at Brandeis University; and "Account of [Hurwitz's] Career."
      - [Folder labeled: Kirkland], 1976 (Folder 14)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's residency at Kirkland College, including student evaluations. Also includes the Spring 1976 issue of the Kirkland literary magazine Dessert at the Plaza, and two Spring Term 1976 event schedules for the Sherman Society of Utica College.
      - For Kirkland seminar, "SFNP", 1975-1976 (Folder 18a)
      - [Envelope labeled: Kirkland seminar folders], 1975-1976 (Folder 18b)
        Additional documents related to Hurwitz's artist-in-residency and seminars at Kirkland College.
      - [Paper bag labeled: Kirkland clippings], 1975-1976 (Folder 19)
        Clippings from the Hamilton College-Kirkland College newspaper The Spectator. Also includes a poem by Ilene Moskin featuring a quote by Hurwitz, and a copy of Hurwitz's "Account of Career."
    - no title (Box C227)
      - L.H. film lists, 1973 (Folder 16)
        To-Do list for Iowa with list of films, list of persons at Kirkland College, tentative program, itinerary, and checklist of films for visit to Kirkland College.
  - Subseries 6, New School, 1946-1957; 1946-1950
    - no title (Box C034)
      - Sharaf's Notes -- 1st seminar in film tech., 1948 (Folder 1b)
        Typed class notes from Hurwitz's Seminar in Film Techniques taught at the New School of Social Research, dated February through May 1948.
      - Native Land-- New School -- seminar in F. techniques, 1948 (Folder 1d)
        Materials related to Hurwitz's "Seminar in Film Techniques," taught at the New School of Social Research in spring 1948. Includes Film Department course description brochure, "Outline of Basic-Need Themes in the Film Native Land" and handwritten notes on Frontier Films, Inc., letterhead.
      - Best Years-- analysis of structure -- notes & questions, ca. 1948; undated (Folder 1f)
        "The Best Years-- Beat breakdown -- outline story in terms of needs" and handwritten notes on Frontier Films, Inc., letterhead. Probably materials for Hurwitz's "Seminar in Film Techniques" taught at the New School in spring 1948.
      - Seminars in film tech -- New School, 1947-1950 (Folder 1g)
        "Dramatic Workshop of the News School for Social Research" course description booklets for school years 1947-1948 and 1949; attendance sheets for classes "T.V. Prod. & Dir. 'C'" (no year given) and "TV Production I" (dated March 13 to May 20, 1950), taught at 432 West 44th Street, NYC (The Actor's Studio); handwritten lecture notes and memos, some on Freedom Road Films, Inc., letterhead.
    - no title (Box C050)
      - Film-TV school catalogues, 1946-1949; 1956 (Folder 15)
    - no title (Box C073)
      - Dramatic Workshop, 1949; undated (Folder 18)
        Correspondence and curriculum notes regarding Hurwitz's appointment as head of the Film, Radio, and Television Department of the Dramatic Workshop & Technical Institute (formerly the Dramatic Workshop of the New School for Social Research). Also includes a Spring/Fall 1949 department brochure.
    - no title (Box C201)
      - [Envelope labeled: Class], 1957 (Folder 14a)
        Class notes, shooting scripts. Materials originally housed in a New School for Social Research envelope addressed to Manfred Kirchheimer.
  - Subseries 7, New York University, 1958-1990; 1959-1984
    - no title (Box C006)
      - Copies of a NY Times article about NYU Film School, 1969 (Folder 4)
        Photocopies of a 1969 New York Times clipping about the Institute of Film and Television at New York University.
      - Misc. Correspondence, 1950s-1960s, 1968-1976 (Folder 11)
        Includes a memo to NYU students.
      - [Correspondence, publications, and personal papers], 1949; 1965-1979 [bulk] (Folder 22)
        Includes correspondence from New York University dean David Oppenheim.
    - no title (Box C016)
      - Film school -- curr. -- New School, etc., 1962; 1966-1967 (Folder 29)
    - no title (Box C021)
      - [Envelope labeled: NYU to file -- AFI], 1971-1972; undated (Folder 4)
        Material concerning the American Film Institute Center for Advanced Film Studies' University Advisory Committee Conference, which Hurwitz sat on. Also included was an untitled script by Vincent Petrillo with a New York University note attached to it.
    - no title (Box C030)
      - [NET project memos, NYU Theatre Program material], 1965-1966 (Folder 40)
    - no title (Box C037)
      - [Envelope labeled: New York University workshop course], 1959-1960 (Folder 1b.3)
        New York University Department of Television, Motion Pictures, and Radio brochure for the Second Annual Summer [1959] Motion Picture Workshop and workshop schedule, with accompanying letter from department chairman Richard Goggin welcoming Hurwitz to the Summer 1960 workshop.
      - [Flex folder labeled: N.Y.U. film workshop course, summer 1960], 1959-1960 (Folder 4)
        Workshop schedule; related correspondence between Haig Manoogian, Hurwitz, and workshop students; student bios, essays, and scripts. Also includes short story clipped from May 1959 Esquire magazine, and prose and poetry by Tom Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C038)
      - [Envelope labeled: N.Y.U. -- Struggle vs. dean 1973, plus misc.] (Folder 13)
        Issues of New York University (NYU) newspaper Washington Square Daily News dated 11/17-19/1973, 11/22-25/1973 and featuring articles about the proposed merger of the undergraduate and graduate departments of the NYU Film Institute. Includes letter from the National Endowment for the Arts inviting Hurwitz to participate in a pilot fellowship program in film and television, and Alan Jones's résumé with cover letter.
    - no title (Box C039)
      - [Bag labeled: Bank statements and insurance policies, etc.], 1975-1980 (Folder 1)
        Includes correspondence regarding Hurwitz's forced retirement from New York University due to age.
    - no title (Box C040)
      - NYU film school brochures, ca. 1967 (Folder 14)
        The Institute of Film and Television at New York University (NYU) brochure; program, degree, and admission requirements, and curriculum. Cover letter from "Jeff."
      - Correspondence -- miscellaneous, 1958-1969 (Folder 18)
    - no title (Box C041)
      - Stanley Faulkner, 1973; 1976-1978 (Folder 69)
        Includes correspondence regarding Hurwitz's claim against New York University.
    - no title (Box C050)
      - N.Y.U. retirement, 1974 (Folder 4)
        Correspondence regarding Hurwitz's Special Retirement Program and the reduction of retirement age at New York University, and photocopies of pages from a guide to academia and income tax.
      - Retirement suit, 1974 (Folder 5)
        New York Times and Time Magazine clippings about age discrimination in the workplace; letter from American Civil Liberties Lawyer to Hurwitz's attorney Stanley Faulkner regarding Hurwitz's case against New York University; and a draft of "Memo to D.O." [likely David Oppenheim, Dean, School of the Arts, NYU].
      - Retirement (N.Y.U.), 1973-1974 (Folder 6)
        Life insurance policy change of beneficiary request form, 5/3/1974 letter from David Oppenheim, Dean, School of the Arts, NYU, announcing Hurwitz's retirement at the end of the semester; letter regarding Hurwitz's retirement benefits program; copies of overview of NYU's special retirement program.
    - no title (Box C057)
      - Miscellaneous LTH papers for archive, 1973-1974; 1980 (Folder 3)
        Includes an agenda for a New York University faculty meeting.
    - no title (Box C062)
      - [Envelope labeled: Names and addresses -- miscellaneous], 1971-1974; undated (Folder 39a)
    - no title (Box C086)
      - NYU Film Institute letter of appointment, 1969-1973 (Folder 5)
        Correspondence about Hurwitz's hiring by New York University (NYU), including letters regarding salary, Hurwitz's terms and conditions, and the proposal to combine the undergraduate and graduate film and television schools. Also includes a clipping from Variety and NYU newsletters with articles regarding Hurwitz.
    - no title (Box C094)
      - [General -- Paul Strand exhibit, NYU Draft, Sophia Delza article, film catalog], 1970-1972; 1983-1984; ca. 1990 (Folder 7)
        Includes a draft of a 1970-1971 New York University report.
      - [General -- retrospective schedule, NYU material, research], 1971; 1983 (Folder 8)
        Includes a Courage to Live press kit; schedule for a Hurwitz retrospective at Melkweg Cinema in Amsterdam and Haags Filmhuis in The Hague; New York University-related notes and inter-office communication; and an issue of Filmmakers Newsletter on anthropology and film.
      - Dean's report 1970-71, 1969-1973 (Folder 24)
    - no title (Box C103)
      - L.H. mail to deal with (N.Y.U. medical ins.), 1975 (Folder 1e)
    - no title (Box C183)
      - Production file, 1969-1974 (Folder 2)
        Class schedules, lists of faculty and students, and school budgets for New York University's Institute of Film and Television, Graduate Division.
      - [Hurwitz portraits], 1969 (Folder 3)
        Five black-and-white photographs of Hurwitz, with memo from the New York University News Bureau.
      - Mandatory retirement, 1973-1974 (Folder 6)
        Correspondence, notes, and materials related to Hurwitz's mandatory retirement from New York University's (NYU) Department of Film and Television. Also includes a copy of the 12/13/1973 issue of the Washington Square Daily News with a back-page notice regarding compulsory retirement and photocopies of pages from the NYU faculty handbook.
      - Seminar, 1970-1972 (Folder 8)
        Notes for an unnamed seminar. Also includes a student contact list from New York University's Department of Film and Television Graduate Division, storyboards for a sequence from The Battle of Algiers 5/7/1971, correspondence, and a New York Times review of a Cézanne exhibition by Hilton Kramer.
      - 1972-1973 budget (Folder 9)
        Budget estimates, with notes on New York University message sheets.
      - D.O. (1970 budget), also (1971) (Folder 10)
        New York University's Institute of Film & Television, Graduate Department, line budgets ("D.O." [David Oppenheim] approved), related memos, and notes.
      - 1968-1969 budget (Folder 11)
        New York University's Institute of Film & Television proposed operational budget for 1968 and memos.
      - Faculty 1/12/73, 1969-1974 (Folder 12)